Guide to the Time Inc. Sports Illustrated Publishing and Business Records 1950s-1993 MS 3009-RG 35
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Sports Illustrated Publishing and Business Records
1950s-1993
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 35
36.6 Linear feet in 36 record cartons, 1 document case, and 1 flat box
Sports Illustrated (SI) launched on August 16, 1954 as a weekly magazine with managing editor Sidney James and publisher Harry Phillips. The Sports Illustrated (SI) Publishing and Business Records contain files from the deparments in charge of permissions, advertising sales, advertising promotion, merchandising, and market research. This record group contains extensive records on the early years of SI including early memoranda from managing editor James in the merchandising files. It also contains extensive records documenting the promotion of SI, particularly to potential advertisers, through awards ceremonies, collaborative events with communities, and scripted presentations to a variety of advertisers during SI's first year of publication. The advertising promotion files also include hundreds of taped interviews with sports figures which SI sent out as part of a tape service to radio and television stations.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials include contracts and are located in box R65. Boxes that are solely audiovisual material are also restricted as unreformatted audiovisual material in the collection is not accessible. Please contact the curator at manuscripts@nyhistory.org regarding access.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Historical Note
Sports Illustrated (SI) launched on August 16, 1954 as a weekly magazine with managing editor Sidney James and publisher Harry Phillips.
According to an unsigned capsule history in the General Files, Time Inc. cofounder and president Henry R. Luce asked executive vice president Howard Black to come up with new publishing venture ideas. Black's May 21, 1953 letter to Luce contained a paragraph reading: "A Sports Weekly -- everything in sports -- hunting, fishing, boating. this would be a picture magazine -- 10 cents a copy." By June 1953, Time Inc. set up a department to develop this magazine.
The "Editorial Notes" in the General Files state that SI was the first Time Inc. magazine to include bylines. It started with well-known sports writers. Later it incorporated articles from famous authors such as "[William] Faulkner and Catherine Drinker Bowen on the Derby," and "Robert Frost on the All-Star Game." Notable sports writers also began their careers as early SI staff writers including Robert Creamer and "Tex" Maule.
For the majority of Time Inc.'s existence, the company maintained a strict separation of editorial from the publishing and business side of each magazine, colloquially called the separation of "church" (editorial) and "state" (publishing). Publishing and Business Management includes the publisher, general manager, business manager, advertising sales, marketing services, letters, circulation, and public relations. The editorial side reported up to the editor-in-chief and the publishing/business side reported up to the corporate business executive which was the president prior to 1960 and the chief executive officer after. Luce structured Time Inc. this way so that the business side could not (in theory) influence the editorial content of the publications. For example, the advertising sales people could not interfere with a magazine's decision to run an article on the dangers of cigarette smoking, even though it might mean losing millions of dollars in tobacco ads.
Citations:
Hooper, Bill. Email to Holly Deakyne, 10 June 2016.
Provenance
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Information about the history of Sports Illustrated and additional records from the publishing and business offices can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Annex Files (MS 3009-RG 39). Records from the editorial offices are in the Time Inc. Sports Illustrated Editorial Records (MS 3009-RG 34).
Scope and Contents
The Sports Illustrated (SI) Publishing and Business Records document the activities of the offices and staff from the publishing and business side of the magazine, not the editorial side. This includes the departments in charge of permissions, advertising sales, advertising promotion, merchandising, and market research. This record group contains extensive records on the early years of SI.
Of note are the photographs and other records about the SI launch party in Keith Morris's files; scripts of presentations to advertisers during SI's first year; a folder on promotion of the first cover and photographs of early store displays and store windows promoting SI in the Merchandising Working File; photographs and audiovisual of early promotional events organized by SI; the extensive run of audio interviews of sports figures conducted by Morris; records regarding Time Inc.'s trial run publishing Women's Sports & Fitness; and records throughout regarding the promotion and announcement of the of the events announcing Sportsman and Sportswoman of the Year. Also in the Merchanding Working File are early memoranda from founding managing editor Sidney James.
Arrangement
Organized into six series:
Series I. General Files
Series II. Department of Permissions and Editorial Courtesies: Nancy Kirkland Files
Series III. Advertising Sales: Director of Market Planning Robert Schreiber Files
Series IV. Advertising Promotion Department Records
Series V. Merchandising Working File
Series VI. Market Research Studies
Advertising -- United States.; Athletes -- United States; Coaches (Athletics) -- United States; Corporations -- History; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporation records; Interviews.; Organization files; Publishers and publishing -- Management; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History; James, Sidney L. (Sidney Lorraine), 1906-2004; Morris, Keith, 1927-1987
- Series I. General Files, 1954-1993; 0.25 Linear feet in 3 folders
  Scope and Contents
  The material in the General Files was found in a stack of Sports Illustrated (SI) material to be filed. It looks like records that were collected to document the history of the magazine although it is not clear who collected them for this purpose.
  Divisional Administration contains early descriptions of SI, business plans from the assistant publisher Dick Neale, early memoranda on staffing and staff lists from the business manager Ray Ammarell, and a publisher's letter on rehearsal issues. Sports Illustrated History starts with an undated list of answers from "Tex," possibly staff writer Tex Maule, answering questions posed by "Mr. Vaughn." While the list of questions is not present, the answers start by defining the role of the sports writer and continue by stating the purpose of sports writing. This folder also includes a 1960 memorandum from managing editor Sidney James to Henry Luce titled "Reprospectus Memo," an analysis by assistant managing editor John "Jack" Tibby on SI in its tenth year, and notes for speeches and other public remarks by James.
  Arrangement
  This series is in alphabetical order with the arrangement imposed by the archivist.
  - Divisional Administration: History of Sports Illustrated, 1954-1993 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 1-2)
  - Sports Illustrated History, 1954-1960 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 3)
- Series II. Department of Permissions and Editorial Courtesies: Nancy Kirkland Files, 1956-1966; 01. Linear feet in 2 folders
  The folders on Policy and Rights History was found in a stack of Sports Illustrated (SI) material to be filed. The contents identify the creator as Nancy Kirkland of the Publisher's Office.
  The records are primarily internal memoranda outlining the operations of the department; defining reproduction and promotion rights; discussing conflicts of interest; handling the requests for reprints; discussing the sale of SI photographs to television networks; setting rates of payment for photographs; and drafting form letters to photographers.
  The main correspondent is publisher Garry Valk although most of the memoranda are from Kirkland to him with a smaller amount from him to her.
  The series remains in original order as it initially was a single folder. The folder was split into two due to overcrowding.
  - Policy and Rights History, 1956-1966 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 4-5)
- Series III. Advertising Sales: Director of Market Planning Robert Schreiber Files, 1964-1977; 0.5 Linear feet in 10 folders
  Biographical Note
  Robert Schreiber was appointed Director of Market Planning for Sports Illustrated (SI) in September 1970. Prior he was in Corporate Marketing and Economic Research. He held the SI role through 1981 before moving into the Magazine Group research department. The department head lists no longer list him after 1985.
  Citation:
  Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society
  Robert Schreiber's files range from his roles in Corporate Research and at Sports Illustrated, but were filed together. The materials are analysis memoranda from Schreiber and reports and studies from outside firms.
  This series is in alphabetical order with arrangement imposed by the archivist.
  - Daily Newspaper: Otto Fuerbringer, 1970 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 6)
  - Daily Newspaper: Schreiber & Whinston Analysis, 1970 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 7)
  - Life: Motivation Analysis, Inc.: Reactions to Life's Food and Movie Magazine, 1970 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 8)
  - Life: Report: Evaluation of Publishing Potential of Monthly Supplements to Life Magazine, 1970 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 9)
  - Life: Study: A Study of the Decay of the Effects Produced by 12 Ads in Life Magazine, 1968 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 10)
  - Magazine Advertising, 1977 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 11)
  - Sports Illustrated: Lieberman Research Inc., 1972 February (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 12)
  - Sports Illustrated: Motivational Analysis, Inc., 1964, 1974 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 13)
  - Sports Illustrated: Louis Harris Associates: Research into a new sports magazine, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 14)
  - Sports Illustrated: RMH Research Inc.: Subscriber Study, 1977 (Offsite-box 4112, Folder 15)
- Series IV. Advertising Promotion Department Records, 1950s-1987; 28.1 Linear feet in 29 record cartons, 1 document case, and 1 flat box
  Women's Sports & Fitness Historical Note
  Billie Jean King and Larry King founded womenSports magazine in 1974 as a response to poor coverage on women athletes in the premier sports magazines at the time, namely SI. They sold the majority of ownership to Charter Publishing in 1976. In 1979 womenSports rebranded as Women's Sports & Fitness (WSF). Around 1986, WSF signed an agreement for a trial run with Time Inc. so Time Inc. could explore acquiring it. Time Inc. ultimately did not acquire WSF.
  Cretaz, Britni de la. An Audience of Athletes: The Rise and Fall of Feminist Sports, Longreads, May 2019, https://longreads.com/2019/05/22/an-audience-of-athletes-the-rise-and-fall-of-feminist-sports/
  The Advertising Promotion Department Records document how Sports Illustrated (SI) was publicized, particularly to potential advertisers, through awards ceremonies, collaborative events with communities, and the dissemination of sports news to radio and television stations through a tape service and press releases; and scripts of presentations to a variety of advertisers during SI's first year of publication. The publicity director and special events director were in charge of organizing the annual announcement for Sportsman or Sportswoman of the Year, and their files include extensive records on this award. This record group also contains all files on Time Inc.'s test run publishing Women's Sports & Fitness.
  - Subseries VI.A. Special Events and Publicity Director Keith Morris Files, 1957-1980; 20.6 Linear feet in 20 record cartons, 1 document case, and 1 flat box
    The staff newsletter FYI states in his 1987 death notice that Keith Morris was the Sports Illustrated (SI) director of publicity and special event for 32 years. The letter from the publisher confirms Morris was part of the founding staff of SI and states he was one of the best known staff members. From 1980 until his retirement in 1986, the Department Heads Lists have him only as the special events director. Prior to SI, he worked in the circulation promotion department for Time Inc. getting Time and Life placed on newsstands and in supermarkets.
    Morris's early files contain some materials addressed to and from Terry Rice. In 1959 FYI describes Terry (Teressa) Rice as the "beautiful publicity woman," but her title isn't recorded until 1970 when she is the SI director of press information.
    Citations:
    Barr, Donald J. "From the Publisher." Sports Illustrated Vault, 13 Apr. 1987, https://vault.si.com/vault/1987/04/13/from-the-publisher.
    Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
    Keith Morris's files document his work organizing and publicizing events and promotional activities for Sports Illustrated (SI). His files also include extensive records regarding the SI tape service which mailed ending interviews of sports figures to radio and television stations.
    Unreformatted audiovisual material in the collection is not accessible.
    Organized into five subsubseries based on the original groupings of records:
    Subsubseries VI.A.1. General Files
    Subsubseries VI.A.2. Awards Files
    Subsubseries VI.A.3. Promotional Events Photographs
    Subsubseries VI.A.4. Recordings of Sports Figures Interviews
    Subsubseries VI.A.5. Promotional Audiovisual Files
    Because the file groupings seemed intentional, folders were kept in their original groups/series. There is some overlapping of subject matter such as awards events in the General Files.
    - Subsubseries VI.A.1. General Files, 1957-1980; 7.25 Linear feet in 8 record cartons
      General Files includes Keith Morris's correspondence and offices files containing memoranda and correspondence arranging collaboration events between professional sports teams or figures and product or company promotions; memoranda and correspondence arranging events honoring professional athletes; correspondence with sports teams and product companies regarding product endorsements; photographs of events; and correspondence to media organizations offering copies of celebrity athlete interviews conducted by SI.
      Issue publicity includes a schedule for publicity events listing people and organizations, but not the type of event (meeting, phone call, appearance); and telegrams to radio stations, sportscasters, and others informing them of articles of interest in the current SI issue.
      Radio and Television Correspondence includes offers for a free weekly mailing of the SI radio tape service to media stations and related correspondence. The tapes contained interviews with sports personalities and editorial commentary.
      Organized by correspondence then by chronologically grouped files by year based on the original order. The 1960 Files, 1961 Files, 1962 Files, and 1962 Large Special Projects were existing folder divisions. Other general files were grouped by year, but without the explicit folder divisions. The divisions for 1971 Files, 1972 files, and 1980 files were devised by the archivist.
      - Correspondence: Miscellaneous, 1960-1962 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 1-3)
      - 1960 Files (Offsite-box -, Folder -)
      - Endorsements by Sports Stars, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 4-5)
      - Sports Illustrated-NBC Radio Campaign, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 6)
      - 1961 Files (Offsite-box -, Folder -)
      - Endorsements by Sports Stars, 1961 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 7-8)
      - Equitable Life Assurance Society, 1961-1963 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 9-11)
      - Staff Memoranda and Publicity Reports, 1957-1961 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 12-13)
      - 1962 Files (Offsite-box -, Folder -)
      - Ad Campaign: Dupont Boys Wear Father-Son, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 14-15)
      - Endorsement: Phillips 66, 1963 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 16)
      - Endorsements: Sales Letters from Sports Stars, 1962 (Offsite-box 4113, Folder 17)
      - Endorsements by Sports Starts, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 1-2)
      - Endorsements: Vitalis, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 3-4)
      - Faces in the Crowd Award of Merit, 1962 September-December (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 5-6)
      - Keystone Camera, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 7)
      - Mallory Hat Program, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 8)
      - Sears Roebuck Program, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 9)
      - 1962 Large Special Projects (Offsite-box -, Folder -)
      - All State Sports Incentive Program, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 10)
      - Bristol Myers: Baseball Promotion, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 11)
      - Bristol Myers: Boxing Promotion, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 12)
      - Byline Club: Kansas City, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 13)
      - Celebrity Tape Service or Women's Show Possibility, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 14)
      - Dial Soap Program, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 15-16)
      - Floyd Patterson Reception, 1962 (Offsite-box 4114, Folder 17)
      - Goodyear Incentive Program, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 1-2)
      - Governors Conference: Sports Program, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 3)
      - Halle Brothers Golf Clinic, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 4)
      - Intercity Bridge Tournament: Minneapolis, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 5)
      - Jim Beatty Luncheon, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 6)
      - Macy's: Valiant Promotion, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 7)
      - National Football Foundation and Silver Anniversary Winners Dinner, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 8)
      - People to People Dinner, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 9-10)
        Includes audiovisual material.
        1 phonograph record (45 rpm); 7 in. On label: "People to People Sports Committee Dinner. Sponsored by Sports Illustrated. Honoring American sports champions and Ed Sullivan. People to People (Leonard Whitcup - Chet Gierlach). Gordon MacCrae and The Merrill Staton Singers."
      - Raytheon Incentive Program (Bowl Games), 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 11)
      - 1962 Silver Anniversary Publicity, 1962-1963 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 12)
      - 1962 Sportsman of the Year (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 13)
      - Touchdown Club Luncheon, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 14)
      - Winter Carnival Television Spectacular, 1962 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 15)
      - 1971 Files (Offsite-box -, Folder -)
      - Endorsements, 1971 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 16-18)
      - Issue Publicity: January-December, 1971 (Offsite-box 4115, Folder 19-30)
      - Radio and Television Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 4116, Folder 1-2)
      - Salesmen's Requests/Small Projects/Special Projects, 1971 January-August (Offsite-box 4116, Folder 3-16)
      - Salesmen's Requests/Small Projects/Special Projects, 1971 September-December (Offsite-box 4117, Folder 1-6)
      - 1972 Files (Offsite-box -, Folder -)
      - Endorsements, 1972 (Offsite-box 4117, Folder 7-11)
      - Issue Publicity, 1972 January-December (Offsite-box 4117, Folder 12-23)
      - Radio and Television Correspondence, 1972 (Offsite-box 4118, Folder 1-2)
      - Salesmen's Requests/Small Projects/Special Projects, 1972 January-June (Offsite-box 4118, Folder 3-15)
      - Salesmen's Requests/Small Projects/Special Projects, 1972 July-December (Offsite-box 4119, Folder 1-9)
      - Armstrong Golf Outing and Acceptances, 1972 (Offsite-box 4119, Folder 10-11)
      - Celanese Ad, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 4119, Folder 12)
      - Chrysler Promotion Lists, 1971? (Offsite-box 4119, Folder 13)
      - Fast Close Color, 1972 (Offsite-box 4119, Folder 14)
      - Heublein, 1972 (Offsite-box 4119, Folder 15)
      - J. C. Penney Promotion, 1972 (Offsite-box 4119, Folder 16-17)
      - J. C. Penney Promotion, 1972 (Offsite-box 4120, Folder 1-3)
      - 1980 Files (Offsite-box -, Folder -)
      - SI/80 Pebble Beach (staff retreat), 1980 (Offsite-box 4120, Folder 4)
      - Weekly Radio Scripts, 1980 (Offsite-box 4120, Folder 5)
    - Subsubseries VI.A.2. Awards Files, 1957-1981; 1.75 Linear feet in 3 record cartons
      Awards Files document the awards events planned or sponsored by Sports Illustrated. The majority of awards in the files were given by SI, specifically the Sportsman or Sportswoman of the Year and the Silver Anniversary All-American Award presented to collegiate football players 25 years after graduation who have since made outstanding social or professional contributions.
      Organized alphabetically by event name.
      - Jaycee-Sports Illustrated Youth Fitness Week Contest and Award, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 4120, Folder 6-9)
      - National Football Foundation and Hall of Fame Dinner, 1958, 1961 (Offsite-box 4120, Folder 10-11)
      - Silver Anniversary All-America Award: Winners 1956-Present (1966), [1967] (Offsite-box 4120, Folder 12)
      - Silver Anniversary All-America Award: General, 1956-1958 (Offsite-box 4120, Folder 13-15)
      - Silver Anniversary All-America Award: General, 1958 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 1)
      - Silver Anniversary All-America Award: Pictures and Bios of Nominees, 1958 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 2)
      - Silver Anniversary All-America Award: Pictures, 1961 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 3)
      - Silver Anniversary All-America Award: Trophy, 1961? (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 4)
      - Silver Anniversary All-America Award: Presentation Pictures, 1965 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 5)
      - Sports Illustrated Design Award, 1959-1963 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 6-8)
        1 audiotape reel: analog, 7 1/2 ips; 7 in., 1/4 in. tape. On side label: "SIDA. SLDAT. James and Goren and Weitz interviews by Patty Cavin. Wash. D.C." On back label: "Patty Cavin - 1) Stella Sloat. 2) Weitz and Goren. 3) James."
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: General: Pictures, 1973-1977 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 9)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: General: Urn, 1960-1974 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 10)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1958: Rafer Johnson, 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 11-12)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1959: Ingemar Johansson (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 13)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1960: Arnold Palmer (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 14)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1962: Terry Baker (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 15)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1968: Bill Russell (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 16)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1969: Tom Seaver (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 17)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1971: Lee Trevino (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 18)
      - Sportsman/Sportswoman of the Year: 1972: Billie Jean King and John Wooden (Offsite-box 4121, Folder 19-21)